A few years ago, my eyes were opened
قبل عدة سنوات مضت فُتحت عيناي
to the dark side of the construction industry.
على الجانب المظلم في صناعة البناء.
In 2006, young Qatari students
عام 2006، طالب قطري شاب
took me to go and see the migrant worker camps.
صحبني للذهاب معه لمخيمات العُمّال المهاجرين.
And since then I've followed the unfolding issue of worker rights.
ومنذ ذلك الحين تابعت القضية المطوية لحقوق العُمّال.
In the last six months, more than 300 skyscrapers
وفي الست أشهر الماضية، أكثر من 300 ناطحة سحاب
in the UAE have been put on hold or canceled.
في الإمارات العربية المتحدة تم تأجيلها أو إلغاؤها.
Behind the headlines that lay behind these buildings
وراء العناوين الرئيسية التي تكمن وراء هذه المبان
is the fate of the often-indentured construction worker.
يقبع مصير عُمّال البناء بالسخرة.
1.1 million of them.
1.1 مليون منهم.
Mainly Indian, Pakistani, Sri Lankan
معظمهم هنود، باكستانيين، سيرلانكيين،
and Nepalese, these laborers risk everything
نيباليين، هؤلاء العُمّال يجازفون بكل شئ
to make money for their families back home.
من أجل توفير المال لأسرهم في أوطانهم.
They pay a middle-man thousands of dollars to be there.
أنهم يدفعون للوسيط آلالاف الدولارات ليكونوا هناك.
And when they arrive, they find themselves in labor camps with no water,
وعندما يصلون، يجدون أنفسهم في مخيمات العُمّال بدون ماء،
no air conditioning, and their passports taken away.
بدون تكييف، ويتم أخذ جوازات سفرهم.
While it's easy to point the finger at local officials and higher authorities,
وبينما من السهل توجيه أصابع الإتهام للمسئولين المحليين والسلطات العليا،
99 percent of these people are hired by the private sector,
99 في المائة من أؤلئك الناس يتم توظيفهم من قبل القطاع الخاص.
and so therefore we're equally, if not more, accountable.
ولذا فنحن نشعر بنفس القدر، إن لم يكن أكثر، بالخضوع للمساءلة.
Groups like Buildsafe UAE have emerged,
مجموعات مثل Buildsafe UAE بدأت في الظهور.
but the numbers are simply overwhelming.
لكن ببساطة الأعداد مذهلة.
In August 2008,
في أغسطس 2008،
UAE public officials noted
لاحظ مسئولون إمارتيون
that 40 percent of the country's 1,098 labor camps
أن 40 في المائة من مخيمات العُمّال ال 1098 في البلاد
had violated minimum health and fire safety regulations.
أنتهكت الحد الأدنى لقوانين الصحة والسلامة من الحرائق.
And last summer, more than 10,000 workers
وفي الصيف الماضي، أكثر من 10 آلالاف عامل
protested for the non-payment of wages,
أحتجوا على عدم دفع أجورهم،
for the poor quality of food, and inadequate housing.
لسوء نوعية الغذاء ، والسكن غير الملائم.
And then the financial collapse happened.
وبعد ذلك حدث الإنهيار المالي.
When the contractors have gone bust,
وعندما أفلس المقاولون،
as they've been overleveraged like everyone else,
لأنهم إستدانوا أكثر مثلما فعل أي شخص آخر،
the difference is everything goes missing,
الفرق هو أن كل شئ يضيع سدى،
documentation, passports,
الوثائق، جوازات السفر،
and tickets home for these workers.
وتذاكر الرجوع إلى الوطن لهؤلاء العُمّال.
Currently, right now, thousands of workers are abandoned.
حالياً، الآن، آلالاف من العمال يتم التخلي عنهم.
There is no way back home.
لا طريق للعودة إلى الوطن.
And there is no way, and no proof of arrival.
وليس هناك طريق، ولا إثبات للوصول.
These are the boom-and-bust refugees.
هؤلاء هم لاجئون للإزدهار والإفلاس.
The question is, as a building professional,
السؤال هو، كمحترفي بناء،
as an architect, an engineer, as a developer,
كمعماريين، كمهندسين، كمطورين،
if you know this is going on,
إذا كنت تعلم أن هذا يحدث،
as we go to the sights every single week,
حيث أننا نذهب الى المواقع أسبوعياً،
are you complacent or complicit
هل نحن راضين أو متواطئين
in the human rights violations?
مع إنتهاكات حقوق الإنسان؟
So let's forget your environmental footprint.
إذاً لننسى تأثيرك على البيئة.
Let's think about your ethical footprint.
لنفكر في تأثيرك الأخلاقي.
What good is it
ما هو الشئ الجيد
to build a zero-carbon, energy efficient complex,
في بناء بدون كربون، مجمع كفؤ في إستخدام الطاقة،
when the labor producing this architectural gem
عندما يكون العُمّال الذين ينتجون هذه التحفة المعمارية
is unethical at best?
غير أخلاقي في أحسن الأحوال؟
Now, recently I've been told I've been taking the high road.
الآن، مؤخراً قيل لي أنني أتخذت الطريق العالي.
But, quite frankly, on this issue,
لكن، بكل صراحة، في هذه القضية،
there is no other road.
ليس هناك طريق آخر.
So let's not forget who is really paying the price of this financial collapse.
لذا ينبغي علينا عدم نسيان من يدفع حقاً ثمن هذا الإنهيار المالي.
And that as we worry about our next job in the office,
وكما أن علينا أن نقلق بشأن مهمتنا المقبلة في المكتب ،
the next design that we can get, to keep our workers.
التصميم القادم الذي سنحصل عليه، للحفاظ على عمالنا.
Let's not forget these men, who are truly dying to work.
دعونا لا ننسى هؤلاء الرجال ، الذين هم حقا يموتون من أجل العمل.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)